Cambridge, Mass. First Church records, 1784-1968.
Congregational Library Archives
- Church organizations, 1813 1934; 1813-1968; 84 Files; (59 volumes, 25 folders)
  - Margaret Shepard Society records, 1830 1932; 1830-1932; 15 Volumes
    - Guild records, 1911 1916; 1911-1916 (Box 5, Volume 23)
  - Maternal Association records, 1833 1856; 1833-1856; 1 Volume
    This subseries contains the records and meeting minutes of the Maternal Association.
    - Records, 1833 1856; 1833-1856 (Box 5, Volume 24)
  - Holmes Chapel Association records, 1857; 1 Folder
    This subseries contains a single stock certificate for the Holmes Chapel Association.
    - Certificate, 1857 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Freedmen's Aid Society records, 1864 1875; 1864-1875; 3 Volumes
    This subseries contains the records of the Freedmen's Aid Society and contains meeting minutes, reports, and financial records.
    - Reports, 1864 1875; 1864-1875 (Box 5, Volume 25)
    - Financial records, 1865 1874; 1865-1874 (Box 5, Volume 26)
    - Records, 1867 1870; 1867-1870 (Box 5, Volume 27)
  - Church Aid Society records, 1870-1875; 2 Volumes
    This subseries contains the records and meeting minutes of the Church Aid Society.
    - Records, 1870 1871; 1870-1871 (Box 5, Volume 28)
    - Records, 1870 1875; 1870-1875 (Box 5, Volume 29)
  - Ladies Union Missionary Society records, 1872 1891; 1872-1891; 4 Volumes
    This subseries contains the records and meeting minutes of the Ladies Union Missionary Society and Young Ladies Missionary Society.
    - Records, 1872 1886; 1872-1886 (Box 5, Volume 30)
    - Records, 1873 1881; 1873-1881 (Box 5, Volume 31)
    - Records, 1887 1892; 1887-1892 (Box 5, Volume 32)
    - Young Ladies Missionary Society records, 1878 1891; 1878-1891 (Box 5, Volume 33)
  - Young People's Alliance records, 1884 1929; 1884-1929; 12 Files; (4 volumes, 8 folders)
    This subseries contains the records of the Young People's Alliance and includes meeting minutes, annual reports, organization manuals, membership list, and a list of officers.
    - Minutes, 1884 1895; 1884-1895 (Box 6, Volume 1)
    - Minutes, 1896 1900; 1896-1900 (Box 6, Volume 2)
    - Annual report, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Constitution and members list, 1898 1914; 1898-1914 (Box 6, Volume 3)
    - Minutes, 1900 1904; 1900-1904 (Box 6, Volume 4)
    - Manuals, 1900 1916; 1900, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Reports, 1905 1906; 1905-1906 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Reports, 1907 1910; 1907-1910 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Reports, 1910 1915; 1910-1915 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Reports, 1915 1920; 1915-1920 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Reports, 1920 1929; 1920-1929 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Officers and calendar, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Sunday School records, 1888 1968; 1888-1968; 5 Files; (2 volumes, 3 folders)
    This subseries contains the records of the Sunday School at the First Church in Cambridge and includes membership records, attendance records, meeting minutes, and historical sketches.
    - Record book, 1888 1889; 1888-1889 (Box 5, Volume 34)
    - Membership roll, 1888 1889; 1888-1889 (Box 8, Volume 1)
    - Attendance records, 1900 1902; 1900-1902 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Attendance records, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Historical sketches, 1940 1968; 1940, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Captains of Ten records, 1889 1932; 1889-1932; 4 Files; (2 volumes, 2 folders)
    The subseries contains the records of the Captains of Ten organization and includes meeting minutes, a historical sketch, and a lecture.
    - Records, 1889 1897; 1889-1897 (Box 6, Volume 5)
    - Records, 1892 1898; 1892-1898 (Box 6, Volume 6)
    - History, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Lecture, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Woman's Foreign Missionary Society records, 1892 1923; 1892-1923; 9 Files; (6 volumes, 3 folders)
    This subseries contains the records of the Woman's Foreign Missionary Society and the Ladies Foreign Missionary Society and includes meeting minutes, the organization's constitution, executive committee minutes, and a letter from Osaka, Japan.
    - Ladies Foreign Missionary Society records, 1892 1898; 1892-1898 (Box 6, Volume 7)
    - Records, 1897 1903; 1897-1903 (Box 6, Volume 8)
    - Ladies Foreign Missionary Society letter from Osaka, Japan, 1903 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Records, 1903 1910; 1903-1910 (Box 6, Volume 9)
    - Records, 1909 1918; 1909-1918 (Box 6, Volume 10)
    - Papers, 1915 1920; 1915-1920 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Executive meeting minutes, 1918 1922; 1918-1922 (Box 6, Volume 11)
    - Records, 1918 1923; 1918-1923 (Box 6, Volume 12)
    - Constitution, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Knights of King Arthur records, 1897 1934; 1897-1934; 4 Volumes
    This subseries contains the records and meeting minutes of the Knights of King Arthur church group.
    - Records, 1897 1904; 1897-1904 (Box 6, Volume 13)
    - Records, 1904 1911; 1904-1911 (Box 6, Volume 14)
    - Records, 1911 1922; 1911-1922 (Box 6, Volume 15)
    - Records, 1923 1932; 1923-1934 (Box 6, Volume 16)
  - Woman's Home Missionary Society records, 1900 1920; 1900-1920; 5 Files; (3 volumes, 2 folders)
    This subseries contains the records and meeting minutes of the Woman's Home Missionary Society and includes a historical sketch and speech notes delivered at the twenty-fifth anniversary of the church organization.
    - Historical sketches, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Twenty-fifth anniversary speech, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Records, 1903 1909; 1903-1909 (Box 6, Volume 21)
    - Records, 1910 1916; 1910-1916 (Box 6, Volume 22)
    - Records, 1916 1920; 1916-1920 (Box 6, Volume 23)
  - Riverside Alliance records, 1900 1928; 1900-1928; 8 Files; (4 volumes, 4 folders)
    This sub series contains the records of the Riverside Alliance and includes meeting minutes, reports, membership records, and organizational pamphlets.
    - Records, 1900 1928; 1900-1928 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Membership records, 1902 1905; 1902-1905 (Box 6, Volume 17)
    - Minutes, 1905 1908; 1905-1908 (Box 6, Volume 18)
    - Records and reports, 1905 1912; 1905-1912 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      These materials were removed from the Riverside Alliance membership records, 1905-1913.
    - Membership records, 1905 1913; 1905-1913 (Box 6, Volume 19)
    - Pamphlets, 1907, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Minutes, 1908 1911; 1908-1911 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Membership records, 1910 1912; 1910-1912 (Box 6, Volume 20)
  - Parish Auxiliary records, 1916 1923; 1916-1923; 1 Volume
    This subseries contains the records and meeting minutes of the Parish Auxiliary.
    - Records, 1916 1923; 1916-1923 (Box 6, Volume 24)